I'm here with John kiraku and those of
us who listen to the radio show we do
we've had him on recently uh to talk
about his story but I wanted you to you
know tell us a little bit about yourself
for those who haven't seen our radio
interview to have some context for what
you uh did in the CIA sure uh my name is
John kiraku I am a former CIA
counterterrorism officer I spent 15
years in the CIA the first half of my
career was in analysis most ly in the
Middle East all of it in the Middle East
and uh the second half of my career was
in counterterrorism operations I was the
chief of CIA counterterrorism operations
in Pakistan after the 911 attacks and um
I led a series of raids One Night in
late March 2002 that resulted in the
capture of Abu zubeda who we believed at
the time was the number three in
al-Qaeda uh we also captured I'm not
allowed to say the number but many
dozens of other Al-Qaeda Fighters I left
the CIA in 2004 to go into the private
sector and in December 2007 I decided to
blow the whistle on the cia's torture
program which I believed was was
patently illegal in addition to being
immoral and unethical I gave a
nationally televised interview on ABC
News with Brian Ross and I said that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners I said
that torture was official US government
policy it was not the result of a rogue
officer as President Bush had intimated
and I said that the the program had been
personally approved by the president
himself as you might imagine the FBI
began investigating me uh the very next
day and uh they investigated me for a
full year from December of 2007 until
December 2008 uh I ended up going up to
Capitol Hill and uh worked as the chief
investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations
Committee and and then in January of
2012 so this is four years and a month
after blowing the
whistle um I was arrested by the FBI I
was charged with five felonies including
three counts of Espionage coming out of
that original ABC news interview of
course I hadn't committed Espionage
those charges were all dropped
eventually
um but to make a long story short I had
to take a plea to a lesser charge to
make the whole thing go away I was more
than a million dollars in debt thanks to
uh legal fees and um the CIA wanted
their pound of Flesh and so I agreed to
take a plea to violating the
intelligence identities protection act
of
1981 I sered 23 months in a federal
prison I have zero
regrets and uh now I've kind of become a
deao spokesman
for issues pertaining to to Liberty and
civil rights civil liberties human
rights uh the rule of law I believe in
the
Constitution and I think that
politically the country is getting to a
point where people understand that and
they're beginning to really appreciate
what that means to stand for Liberty in
the
Constitution did you do interrogation
work I did uh not the violent torture
interrogation work I was always the good
cop at the CIA and so when we would
capture prisoners my Arabic was
absolutely excellent so I would sit down
with these prisoners at first and begin
interviewing them more often than not
they uh did not want
to have a conversation this was in
Pakistan this was in Pakistan would you
go into a room like this like we're in
oh none of the rooms were as nice as not
as this H okay no so but would you have
a little desk or a table right had a
table that had an eyebolt uh uh in it so
we could chain the The Prisoner to the
table so he was a metal table or it was
a metal table yeah real cold uh no that
came later okay that came later in the
secret sites so you'd come in in a
little small table similar to the size
of this table and I would
say Will May peace be upon you will you
cooperate with us sometimes they said
yes usually they said no even if they
said no I'd press them a little bit
would you like to have so how would they
say yes if they were did they say it
with pride or with desperation or with
resignation they said it with
resignation the first one that ever said
yes to me I said
really and he said yes and I said why
would you cooperate with me and he looks
at me and he says because I'm your
prisoner I get nothing out of not
cooperating yeah I said good answer and
he really did cooperate I mean I laid
out maps of the Border area in front of
him and he told me like foot by by foot
how he got across the mountains through
the passes from Afghanistan to Pakistan
he identified the locations of the safe
houses that Al-Qaeda was using both
along the border on the Pakistani side
and then in the cities which we then
used to raid those new new uh houses and
and capture even more Al-Qaeda prisoners
so you know the ones that said yes and
cooperated gave us great stuff the ones
who said no by and large went to
Guantanamo and the important ones who
said no went to a secret
site it wasn't nice at the secret site
were you in charge of sending them to
which one they went to well I would make
a call and I'd say where do you want
them to go and uh they had read at
headquarters they had read my reporting
who had been Cooperative who hadn't been
Cooperative most of them we would just
load onto a C12 and they would fly to
Cuba and the others we would send a
different way what was their body
language like when you would would they
heard their go or they went no they're
just going to go you know they were
mostly so they sff Dazed And so confused
by what was happening to them most of
them just just walked like sheep onto
the back of the of the plane why were
they
dazed because this was all all of this
is happening in the middle of the night
right so they're exhausted they're
terrified they've just escaped from
torab Bora which we bombed the Daylights
out of
and uh and here at 2:00 in the morning
the Americans broke down the door and
just grabbed them now a lot of them were
married and had kids so we separated the
women and children from The Men We ended
up sending the women and children just
back to their home countries but we
didn't tell the prisoners that so we we
LED them to believe that we still had
the the wives in custody were these all
Al-Qaeda or other groups too Taliban
every once in a while we would capture
somebody else we we caught several
Taliban not a lot but a handful we
caught a whole house full of ji Muhammad
the Kashmir separatist group and then we
would get a lot of Egyptian Islamic
Jihad eij guys now they had merged with
Al-Qaeda but they still kept kind of a
separate ethnic identity because they
were all Egyptians in Pakistan in
Pakistan they came over there to help or
oh yeah they went to see Iman is aahi
the who's now the head of uh of alqaeda
was the founder of Egyptian Islamic
Jihad he was one of the masterminds of
the saddad assassination in
1978 so um when he pledged fty to Usama
Bin Laden he took the entire group with
him and eij merged into
Al-Qaeda what was your favorite thing
about your experience with the Pakistani
people with the Pakistani
people I did actually become friends
with my Pakistani counterparts as crazy
as that might sound because because you
can't really trust anybody in Pakistan
they're working both sides of the of the
fence right they're they're working with
you to help capture these people yet
they created the Taliban do you know how
the Taliban were created no how was it
created well first look at the word
Taliban Taliban is a plural of Talib
which means student or
students so the pakistanis were having a
problem with their trucks their trucks
were being hijacked as they were
crossing Afghanistan on the way to Iran
just to trade to deliver goods and so
benzer B came up with this
idea why don't we take some of these
students some of these Taliban that we
have in the madrasas here in Pakistan we
have them ride with the trucks on the
truck drivers or ride in the trucks with
the truck drivers so that they can
protect the truck as it's Crossing
Afghanistan and they did that for a
while and it worked people stopped
attacking the trucks and then they said
said well wouldn't it be more efficient
instead of leaving these guys in the
trucks all the time just to put them in
the Villages that line the road
connecting Pakistan to Iran across kahar
and Helman provinces in southern
Afghanistan well once these guys got
into these Villages they decided they're
taking over The Villages so rather than
you know running for the Village Council
or becoming the May or whatever they
just decided I'm one of the Taliban
we're these students that just arrived
here these Villages are ours now and
they were ethnic pashos and the
villagers were ethnic pashos and you
know Law and Order can be a good thing
when there's a lack of Law and
Order so that's how the Taliban were
born and they became more and more
fundamentalist more and more radicalized
very well-armed so they were actually a
creation of the Pakistani intelligence
service this was a creation that got out
of hand and just spun out of control
now you've got the pakistanis who
created the Taliban also helping us
capture Taliban and
Al-Qaeda while at the same time funding
and arming Kashmir separatist groups so
who do you trust you can't trust anybody
you just have to hope that they're going
to be the good guys on the operation
with you and then what they do in their
spare time just hope that it doesn't
cause you any damage
so I became friendly with these guys to
the point where they had me over to
their house for dinner I met their wives
and kids and um and everything was uh
was copacetic were these small homes or
big homes or very small homes the only
big homes were were the generals homes
they were all corrupt Taliban generals
oh no no Pakistani generals who were
taking money from the Taliban who are
growing Poppy and selling heroin and you
know I thought the Taliban banned this
the growing of poppies in Afghanistan is
that true that's what they like to tell
everybody that's their pitch in fact um
uh poppy cultivation was banned until
the 911 attacks and so they decided that
they just needed the money more than
they needed to ban drugs and now the
whole country is just covered in heroin
poppy but but but the Taliban banned it
prior to 911 yes they did and virtually
out why did the 911 thing change their
mind about legalizing well because drug
use drug addiction is unlam right the
Quran specifically says not to do things
like that but they decided that their
survival was more important than a
strict uh adherence to the coron so they
legalized it to raise funds to battle
America when they came into Afghanistan
cor correct now the irony of this is
Afghanistan produces 93% of the world's
heroin 93% of the world's heroin almost
all of it goes to Iran and Russia
and so Iran has the highest opioid
addiction rates in the world followed
closely by
Russia none of that heroin makes its way
here does it go to Europe though right
some of it goes to Europe but most of it
Iran and Russia so do our troops like
protect those poppy fields or why don't
we stomp that out since we're drug
Warriors I'll I'll tell you a story when
I was the chief investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee I
wanted to do a an indepth report on Cy
cultivation in Afghanistan so I flew to
Afghanistan and I flew into bamir
airbase and I told U my contact there I
need to go to lashara which is the
capital of Helman province that is the
center of the world's heroin
cultivation no it's too dangerous I said
no I have flag status because I'm a
senior Congressional staff I'm saying
we're going to go so we got in a
helicopter and we went
and I had a translator with me I don't
speak pashu and we found a poppy farmer
in his field cultivating the the poppy
and I asked him quite naively in
retrospect why don't you grow instead of
poppy things with two growing Seasons
you can grow uh winter wheat summer
wheat pomegranates tomatoes onions he
has this look of exasperation on his
face he
says the Americans told me in 2001 that
if I told them where the Arabs were I
could grow as much poppy as I wanted now
you come here and you tell me I can't
grow
poppy and I said what Americans told you
in 2001 you could grow poppy well I know
who the only Americans were in
Afghanistan in
2001 and my military Handler says we
have to end this interview we've got to
go back to buam and that was the end of
it so later on I met with the British
ambassador to Afghanistan and the
Italian Ambassador and they said the
same thing that they can't Wipe Out the
poppy crop we can't because if we use
Napalm that's a war crime if we use
Roundup anytime any Afghan child is born
with a birth defect or with mental
retardation or whatever they're going to
blame us because we poisoned the
atmosphere right we poisoned the
environment we keep that in Quaker roats
for us do you yeah right keep it in
Quake roads for us to eat which we eat
every day but the bottom line is that
that Poppy that heroin just doesn't come
here it's not our
problem but it does it does it does it
decrease Kim okay sure excuse me one
second